<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here beginneth the lyf of the moste myscheuoust Robert the deuyll whiche was afterwarde called ye seruaunt of god</title>
            <title>Robert the Devil.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1500</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21070</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106792</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842502</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842502</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10798)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 448:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here beginneth the lyf of the moste myscheuoust Robert the deuyll whiche was afterwarde called ye seruaunt of god</title>
                  <title>Robert the Devil.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Enprynted in fletestrete in the sygne of the sonne by Wynkyn de worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1500?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Robert le diable.</note>
                  <note>Title from caption title, leaf A2r.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>31 lines a page--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴ C D⁴ E⁶.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks leaf A1, title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Here beginneth the lyf of the moſte myſcheuouſt Robert the deuyll whiche was afterwarde called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruaunt of god.</head>
            <p>IT befel in tyme paſt there was a duke in nor mandye whiche was called ouberte the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che duke was paſſinge ryche of goodes &amp; alſo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous of lyuynge and loued and dred god aboue al thinge and dede greate almoſſe dedes and exceded all other in ryghtwyſneſſe and iuſtice / and mooſte cheualrouſe in dedes of armes and noble actes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge. this duke helde open hous vpon a criſtmaſſe daye in a towne whiche was called Nauerne vpon the ſeyne To the whiche courte came al the lordes and noble blode of Normandye. And bycauſe this noble duke was not maryed his lordes and nobles with one aſſente beſought hym to marye and take a wyfe / to thentente that his lygnage myghte be multyplyed there by / and that they myghte haue a ryghte heyre to enheryte his londes after his dyſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. To the whiche requeſte this good duke anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſayde. My lordes what thynge that ye thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke beſt for me to do ſhal be done / vpon a condicion in that ye wyl that I be maryed that ye puruey me a wyf accordinge to myne eſtate for and yf I ſhold coueyte ony heyer or noblyer of blode tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am my ſelf that myght not ſtonde with ryght. and yf I ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke one that is not of ſo noble an houſe as I am that ſholde be to me grete ſhame &amp; al my lygnage wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore me thynke it were better y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I kepte me as I am than to do that thynge that ſholde not be myne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte
<pb facs="tcp:7164:2"/> and afterwarde repente me. Whan thiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des were ſpoken &amp; well conſydered by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes that ſtode there preſent then there roſe vp a wyſe baron and ſayde to the duke. My lorde ye ſpeke very wyſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and lyke a noble prince / but yf it pleaſe your hye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe to gyue audience and here me ſpeke I ſhal ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we you of a certayne perſone / of whome ye ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioye your ſelf to here of her. and the whiche ye ſhal obteyne I knowe well. Than anſwered the duke and ſayde. ſhewe me than who that perſone is / gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious lorde ſayd the baron vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke. the duke of bourgone hath a doughter whiche excedeth all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in beaulte curteſye and debonayre wyſdome &amp; good maners the whiche ye may haue yf ye wyl de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre her. for I know well there wyll noo man ſaye naye therto. To the whiche the good duke anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red and ſayde. that lady playſed hym ryght well &amp; that the baron had gyuen hym good and wyſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. And in ſhorte tyme after that this lady was de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded of her fader the duke of bourgone. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che gaue hym her wyllyngly. And thenne theyr bridale was kept honourably whiche were to lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to wryte.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the duke of Normandy with grete royalte brought his wyfe the doughter of the duke of bour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gon in to roan in Normandy after he had maried her.
<pb facs="tcp:7164:2"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut scenes from the life of royal couple</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>AFter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the forſayde Duke hadde maryed the ſayde lady he broughte her with a grete company of barons knyghtes &amp; ladyes with greate triumphe and glorye in to the londe of normandye and in to the Cyte of Roan / in whiche Cyte ſhe was honourably receyued and with grete melodye &amp; there was grete amyte betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bourgonyons &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7164:3"/> the normans whiche I lete paſſe. for to come y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoner to my mater. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſayd duke and ducheſſe lyued to gyder the ſpace of .xviii. yere withoute ony chylde whether it were goddes wyll it ſholde be ſo. or it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re thorowe theyr owne defaulte I can not Iuge it for it were better other whyle that ſome people had no chylderne. and alſo it were better for the fader &amp; moder to gete no chyldern then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e for lacke of chaſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge / the chyldern and fader and moder ſholde al go to the deuyll. yet were theſe duke and ducheſſe de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoute people whiche loued and drede god and gaue grete almes &amp; what tyme this Duke wolde meddle with his lady he euer prayed to god to ſende him a chylde to honoure and ſerue god and to multyplye and fortefye his lygnage / but nother with prayer nor with almes dedes this good duke and ducheſſe coude gete no chyldern.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How vpon a tyme this Duke and ducheſſe wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked allone ſore complaynynge the one to the other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they coude haue no chylde togyder</head>
            <p>VPon a tyme this duke &amp; ducheſſe walked and the duke began to ſhewe his mynde to his lady ſaynge thus madame we be not fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te in ſo moche that we canne gete no chylderne and they that made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maryage betwene vs both they dyde grete ſynne for I beleue &amp; ye had ben gyuen to an other man ye ſholde haue had chyldern and I al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo yf I hadde an other ladye / this Lady vnderſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſayenge ſhe anſwered ſoftly / ſayenge thus good lorde we muſte thanke god of that whyche he ſendeth vs &amp; take it pacyently of what ſo euer it he.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:3"/>
            <head>¶ How roberte the deuyll was conceyued and how hys moder gaue hym to the deuyll in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cepcyon
<figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut couple in bed</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>THys duke vpon a tyme rode oute on hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge in a grete angre and penſifnes for ough that he coude haue no chylde ſore complaynage ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enge thus to hymſelfe / I ſee many wymmen haue many fayre chyldren in whyche they enioye gretly them by whyche I ſee well that I am hated of god &amp; meruayle it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I fall not in diſpayre for it greue the me ſo ſore at my herte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can gete no chyldren
<pb facs="tcp:7164:4"/> hen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll whiche is alwaye redy to deceyue ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kynde. tempted the good duke &amp; troubled his myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſo that he wyſt not what to do nor ſaye. thus mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued he left his huntynge and went home to his pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lays were he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de his lady alſo vexed &amp; moued as he come home he toke her in his armes &amp; kyſſed her and dyde his wyll with her ſayenge his prayers to our lorde. in this wyſe O lorde ieſu I beſeche the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye gete a chylde at this houre by the whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſte be honoured &amp; ſerued. but the lady beinge ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re moued ſpake thus folyſſhly &amp; ſayd in the deuyls name be it in ſoo moche as god hath not the power that I conceyue and yf I be conceyued with chylde in this houre I gyue it to the deuyl body and ſoule and this ſame houre that this duke &amp; duches were thus moued the ſayde lady was conceyued with a man chylde whiche in his lyf wrought moche miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chefe as ye ſhall here after here / but afterwarde he was conuerted and dyde grete penaunce and dyed a holy man as is ſhewed here after.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert the deuyll was borne and what grete payne his moder ſuffred in his byrth.</head>
            <p>THis ducheſſe as ye haue herd before was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued with the forſayde chylde whiche ſhe bare .ix. monethes as comunly women go with chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / and ye may well perceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this lady coude not be delyuered without grete payne for ſhe traueylled more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a moneth. &amp; yf good prayers had not ben and almes dedes good werkes &amp; grete penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne for her / ſhe had deyed of chylde for all the ladyes
<pb facs="tcp:7164:4"/> &amp; gentylwome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were with her wened ſhe wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de haue peryſſhed &amp; deyed in trauayly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. wherfore they were gretly abaſſhed &amp; aferde with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe noyſe &amp; tokens that they herde &amp; ſe in the byr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the of the ſayde Robert the deuyll in that this chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de was borne / the ſkye waxed as derke as though it had ben nyghte as it is ſhewed in olde cronycles that it tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred and lyghtned ſo ſore that men thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghte the firmament had ben open &amp; all the worlde ſholde haue peryſſhed. And there blewe ſoo moche wynde oute of the .iiii. quarters of the worlde &amp; was ſuche ſtorme and tempeſt that al the hous trembled ſo ſore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhoke a grete pece of it to the erth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al they that were in the hous wened y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world had bene at an ende &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the hous &amp; al ſhold haue ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken but in ſhort tyme it pleaſed god that all this trouble ceaſed &amp; the weder clered vp &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde was broughte to the chyrche to be cryſtned whiche was named Robert. This chylde was a large of ſtature at his byrth &amp; he had ben a yere olde wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the people had grete wonder. and as this chylde was a bery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the chyrche to be cryſtened &amp; home ayene it neuer ſeaced cryenge and houlynge. and in ſhorte ſpace he had longe teeth wherwith he bote y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noryſſhes pappes in ſuche wyſe that there was noo woman durſte gyue hym ſouke for he bote of the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of theyr breſtes. Wherfore they were feyne to gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hym ſouke and to brynge hym vp with an horne and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was twelue moneth olde he coude ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and go allone better than other chylderne that were thre yere olde. and the elder that this chylde ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte
<pb facs="tcp:7164:5"/> waxed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more curſter and wyckedder he wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for as ſone as he coude goo allone there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man nor woman that coude rule hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he founde or coude come by ony chylderne he ſmote and bote and caſte ſtones at them and brake theyr armes and legges and neckes and ſcratte out their eyen oute of theyr heddes and there in was all his pleſure and the lordes and gentylles that ſawe this had grete delyte there in wenynge to them it hadde bene but the youthe and wantoneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Howe all the chylderne with one aſſente named this chylde Roberte the deuyll.</head>
            <p>THis chylde with in fewe yeres growe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilouſly and more and more encreſed of al and boldnes and ſhrewdnes / &amp; ſet by no correccyon but was euer ſmytinge &amp; caſtinge and curſed dedes doinge to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he myghte mete in the ſtretes in ſo moche that there was nother man ne woman nor chylde that durſt mete with hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but fled a waye for fere &amp; drede as the deuyll fleeth frome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. &amp; ſome tyme there gadred to gyder al the boyes of the ſtrete to fyghte with hym / but whan they ſee hym come they durſte not abyde hym / but cried one to an other here cometh the wode Robert an other many cryed here cometh the curſed madde robert &amp; ſome cryed here cometh robert the deuyl &amp; thus cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge &amp; howly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge they voyded all the ſtretes for they durſt not abyde &amp; loke hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face / and forth with the chylderne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knewe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one aſſent called hym robert y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll whiche name he kepte duringe his
<pb facs="tcp:7164:5"/> lyf &amp; ſhall do as longe as the worlde ſtondeth / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this chylde was. ſeuen. yere olde or there aboute the duke his fader / ſeynge and conſyderynge his wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked condicions called hym and ſayde vnto hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus my ſone me thynke it neceſſary and tyme / for me to gete you a wyſe ſcole mayſter and put you to ſcole / to lerne vertues and doctrine for ye be of age ynou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe and whan the duke had thus ſayde / he betoke his ſone to a good diſcret and wyſe ſcole mayſter to rule and teche hym al good condicions &amp; maners</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert kylled his ſcole mayſter.</head>
            <p>IT fell vpon a daye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſcole mayſter ſhold chaſtyſe robert &amp; wolde haue made him to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue left his curſed condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; miſcheuous dedes but robert gate a murderer or bodkin &amp; thraſt his mayſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in the bely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his guttes fell at his fete and ſo fel downe dede to the erth. and robert threwe his boke ayenſt the walles in deſpyte of his mayſter ſaynge thus now haue I taughte the that neuer preſte nor clerke ſhal correcte me nor be my mayſter and from thens forth there coude noo ſcole mayſter be founde that was ſo bolde to take in honde to teche and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte this Robert but were gladde to let hym allone and haue his owne wayes / and he put hymſelfe to vyce &amp; myſchef and curſſidnes &amp; to no maner of ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue nor grace nor none wolde ne lerne for noo man lyuynge / but mocked with god &amp; holy chyrche and whan he came in to the chyrche &amp; fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the preſtes &amp; clarkes ſingy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge goddes ſeruyce / he came preuely behynde them &amp; caſte aſſhes or duſt in to theyr mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes in diſpyte of god / And whan he ſawe ony bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:7164:6"/> in the chyrche beſy in theyr prayers he wolde to me behynde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſowſe in the necke that theyr hedes kyſſed the grounde in ſoo moche that euery creature banned and curſed hym for his wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dedes doynge / And the noble Duke his fader ſeynge this myſcheuous diſpoſicyon &amp; curſed lyf of his ſone he was ſo angry &amp; ſore vexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym ſelfe that he wyſſhed hym ſelf many tymes dede &amp; out of the worlde. And the ducheſſe in lyke wyſe was gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly moued &amp; moche ſorowful / by cauſe of the miſche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous lyf of her ſone. ſaynge to her lorde in this wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe my lorde our ſone is now of ſufficient age / and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to bere armes wherfore me thynke it were beſte that ye made hym knyght yf than he wolde remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre thordre of knighthode wherby he myght chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge his condicyons and leue his wyckedneſſe. The Duke was here with all content. And Roberte had at that tyme but eyghtene yere of age.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert the deuyll was made knyghte by the Duke his fader.</head>
            <p>THis duke aſſembled vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a hye feeſt of whit ſontyde al his barons &amp; nobles of his londe &amp; the next of his kyn &amp; frendes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me he called his ſone to hym ſaynge thus. herke my ſone robert and take hede what I ſhall tell you. It is ſo that by thaduyſe of my counſell and good fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des I am nowe aduyſed to make you a knyghte to thentent that ye with other knyghtes ſholde be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t occupye &amp; haunte cheualrye and knyghtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicyon to thentente that ye ſhall leue and foryete
<pb facs="tcp:7164:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> your vices &amp; vylaynous werkes &amp; moſte hartful lyf Robert herynge this anſwered his fader the duke. I ſhall doo youre commaundement but as for the order of knyghthode I ſet no thynge therby. for the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is no degre ſhall cauſe me leue my condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nor make me to chaunge my lyfe nor to breke my wyl For I am not in that mynde to doo ony better than I haue done hetherto / nor alter myne olde coſtume nor to amende for no man lyuynge it was the coſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of that londe that on whitſonyght the chyrche ſholde be watched and tended with moche people. And theder ranne this robert lyke a madde man be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinge and bonchy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and ouerthrowynge al theym that came in his waye / feringe nother god nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll. and he was neuer ſtyll of all that nyghte and in the mornynge whan it was daye Roberte was made knyghte. Thenne this duke commaunded a tournayment or iuſtynge to be made in whiche tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naymente the ſayde robert wrought mayſtries &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de meruaylous dedes of armes in kyllinge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge doune horſſe &amp; man noo man refuſinge nor ferynge / but bare alle to the grounde that came in his waye. of ſome he brake armes and ſome legges ſome theyr neckes or bare them thorowe and kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them out of the honde. frome hym wente none vnmarked in whiche iuſtynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd robert kylled x. horſes / the duke heringe how his ſone myſcheued and murdred all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came in to his hondes he wente himſelf in to the tournaymente &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon a grete payne / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery manſholde ſeaſe &amp; renne no more. thenne Robert rored for anger as he had ben
<pb facs="tcp:7164:7"/> wode &amp; wolde not obeye his fader co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement but abode ſtyll in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fylde ſmyty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; no thynge ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe moche worſe than he dyde before. and had no pite nother of horſe nor man ſo that he kylled of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte valiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes knyghtes that thether were comen to tournaye. than euery man cried vpon Robert to ſeſe but it auailed not for he wold not ſeſe for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor there was no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo bolde to encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre hym. for bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ſo ſtronge this robert dyde ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che miſchefe that all the peple were in a rore &amp; aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled all with one aſſent in a grete angre and ranne to the duke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnynge ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thus lord ye be gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to blame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſuffre youre ſone to doo as he doth we beſeche you for goddes ſake to fynde ſome reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye for hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cauſe him to ſeaſe or leue his miſrule.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Robert the deuyll rode aboute the countree of normandy robbynge ſtelinge morderynge &amp; bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge chyrches abbayes &amp; other holy places of reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion &amp; forſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of women &amp; rauiſſhy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</head>
            <p>Than whan Robert ſe there was no man mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re left in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fylde &amp; that he coude do no more miſchefe there. than he toke his horſe with the ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree to ſeke aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tures &amp; began to do euery daye more harme than other. for he forſſed &amp; rauyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed maydens &amp; wyues withoute nombre he kylled murdred ſo moche peple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was pyte / alſo he rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed chyrches abbayes hermitages &amp; fermes. there was not an abbaye in all the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey but he rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed chyrches abbayes hermitages &amp; fermes. there was not an abbaye in all the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey but he robbed &amp; pylled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. theſe wycked dedes of Robert came to the eres of the good duke. &amp; all they that were thus robbed &amp; rebuked / came to complayne of the grete
<pb facs="tcp:7164:7"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut monk and two gentlemen</figDesc>
               </figure> outrage and ſuppreſſion done by Robert and ſtylle was doynge thorowe out all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countree. One ſayd my lorde your ſone hath forſſed my wyfe. an other ſayd he hath rauiſſhed my doughter. the other ſayd he hath ſtolen my goodes &amp; robbed my hous. &amp; the other ſayde he hath wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded me to deth with many ſemblable offences. Thus lay they greuouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnynge before the good Duke that grete pyte it was there for to ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good duke hery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the greuous and lamentable complayntes of the great murdre done. by roberte his ſone thorough oute all the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:7164:8"/> of Normandye. Than his herte was ſubpreſſed with ſo greate ſorowe and thoughte that the ſalte t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res breſte oute of his eyen. &amp; wepte tenderly &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. O ryght wyſe god creatoure of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; erth. I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſo many tymes prayed the to ſende me a chylde &amp; all my delyte was to haue a ſone. to thentente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I myght of hym haue grete Ioye and ſolace And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we I haue one. the whiche doth my herte ſo moche payne ſorowe and thoughte that I wote in no wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe what to begynn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor to doo nor ſaye therto. but good lorde only I crye vpon the for helpe and reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye to be a lytell releaſed of my payne and ſorowe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the Duke ſent oute men of armes for to ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke roberte his ſone the whiche robert toke them all and put oute theyr eyen in deſpite of his fader and ſente them ſo home ayen.
<figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut battle scene</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THere was a knyght of the dukes hous whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che perceyued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this good Duke was very ſorowful &amp; penſyfe &amp; knewe no remedye then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c this knyghte ſpake &amp; ſayde to hym. My lorde I wold ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſe you to ſende for youre ſone robert &amp; let hym be brought to your preſence / and there before your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and nexte frendes to rebuke hym. and than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to leue his curſed lyf. &amp; yf he wyll not / ye to do iuſtice vpon hym as on a ſtraunge man / here to the Duke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented and thoughte the knyght ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue hym good counſell. and incontynent he ſente out men to ſeke robert. and in ony wyſe they to brynge hym to his preſence this robert herynge of the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playntes made of alle the people vpon hym vnto his fader and that his fader hadde ſent out men to take hym wherfore al theym that he coude gette he put out theyr cyen / and ſo he toke the men that his fader ſende for hym and put out theyr eyen in deſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of his fader and whan he had thus blynded his faders ſeruauntes he ſayde to theym in mockynge ſyrs nowe ſhall ye ſlepe the better go nowe home to my fader and tell him that I ſet lytell by hym &amp; by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe he ſendeth you to brynge me to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore to his diſpyte I haue put oute youre eyen. &amp; therfore was robert hated both of god &amp; of the worlde &amp; his viceous and mooſt curſed werkes were ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen thorowe out all cryſtendome. Theſe poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes whiche the Duke hadde ſent for robert his ſone / came home with grete payne and in grete he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyneſſe ſaynge thus o good lorde ſee how your ſone robert that ye dede ſende vs fore hath arrayd vs: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7164:9"/> blynded vs. the good Duke ſeynge his men in this caſe / he wexed very angry and full of yre and bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to compaſſe in his mynde how and by what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he might come by to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid robert his ſone</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the duke of normandye made a proclama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion thorugh oute his londe. how men ſholde take robert his ſone with all his companye and brynge hym euerychone to priſon.</head>
            <p>THan ſpake a wyſe lorde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dukes counſell ſaynge thus my lord take no more thought nor be no more penſyfe. for ye ſhal neuer ſe the daye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> robert your ſone wyll come in your preſence in ſo moche as he hath done ſo grete and greuouſe offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces to your commons and youre owne meſſengeres that ye ſende for hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but it were of neceſſyte for you to correcte and punyſſhe hym for his grete offences that he dayly doth &amp; hath done for we fynde it wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lawe byndeth you there to. The duke wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge to accomplyſſhe the councell of his lordes ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de oute meſſangers in all the haſte / vnto all portes good townes and barones / thorugh out all his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedome commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge on his behalfe all ſhryues bayllifes or other offycers to do theyr vttermoſte dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygence to take robert his ſone priſoner &amp; to holde and kepe hym ſurely in priſon with all his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and affinite. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> robert herde of this proclama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion he with all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany were ſore aferde of the Dukes malyce. and whan roberte ſee this was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooſte oute of his wytte for wode angre and whet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted his teeth lyke a bore and ſware a grete othe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge
<pb facs="tcp:7164:9"/> thus that he wolde haue open warre ayenſte his fader and ſubdewe and ſpyll all his lordſhyppe</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Howe robert made hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtronge hous in a derke thycke wyldernes where he wroughte myſchefe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon &amp; aboue al meſure or naturell reaſon
<figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of home construction</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>THen whan robert had herde &amp; knowen of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſayde thynges he lette make in a thycke wylde foreſte a ſtronge hous where in he made his dwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge place and in this place it was wylde and ſtronge &amp; more meter for wylde beeſtes than for ony peple to abyde in / &amp; there robert aſſembled and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany al the moſte miſcheuoſte &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt theues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he coude fynde or here of in his faders
<pb facs="tcp:7164:10"/> londe to wete morderes theues ſtrete robers rebelles brenners of chyrches and houſes forſers of women robbers of chyrches &amp; the moſte wyckedeſte &amp; curſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſte theuis that were vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne robert had ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered to do him ſeruice wherof he was capteyn &amp; in the forſayde wylderneſſe Robert w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his companye dyd ſo moche miſchefe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge can tel he mordred marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye no man durſt lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke out nor come a brode for fere of robert &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye of whom euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was a ferde. for they robbed all the countree in ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man durſt loke ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / but that they were kylled of robert or his men al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo poore pylgremes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wente on pylgremage were murdred by robert &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye in ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry man fledde frome them lyke as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepe fled fro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wolfe for they were as wode as wolues war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge ſleinge al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they coude come by. &amp; thus robert &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye led an vngracious lyf. alſo he was a grete glotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of etynge &amp; drinkinge &amp; neuer faſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge though it were neuer ſo grete a faſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge day. In len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or on ymberdayes heete fleſſhe as well on frida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes as on ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dayes. but after he had done al this miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chefe he ſuffred grete payne as here aft<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> ye ſhal here</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert the deuyll kylled .vii. heremytes.</head>
            <p>IT befell vpon a tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> robert whiche euer I<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>magened &amp; ſtudyed in his mynde how &amp; by what meane he might do moſte myſchef &amp; murdre as he had ben euer acuſtomed before he rode out of his hous or theuiſſhe neſte to ſeke his pray. &amp; in the myddel of the wode he ſawe .vii. holy heremytes to
<pb facs="tcp:7164:10"/> whome he rode as faſte as he coude with his ſwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de redydrawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke a man oute of his mynde &amp; there he ſlewe this .vii. heremites y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche were bolde &amp; good men but they were ſo vertuoꝰ &amp; holy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fred the marterdom for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had thus ſlayne theſe .vii. deuoute me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſpake i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mocka<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge &amp; ſayd I haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de here a neſte of a many pope holy horſons whome I haue ſhauen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crounes I trow they be dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke they were wonte to knele vpon theyr knees and nowe they lye vpon theyr backes there dyde robert a curſed dede &amp; blode ſhedynge in deſpyte of god and holy chirche. &amp; after that he had done this myſcheuous dede he rode oute of the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de lyke a deuyll out of helle ſemynge worſe thanne wode &amp; his clothes were all dyed rede with the blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had murdred &amp; ſlayne. &amp; thus a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed he rode ouer the feldes. &amp; clothes hondes face all were rede of the blode of the holy heremytes. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he had ſo pyteouſly murdred in the wylderneſſe</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert the deuyll rode to his moder the Du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheſſe of normandye beynge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtell of darques where ſhe was come to a feſte</head>
            <p>ROberte rode ſo ferre &amp; ſo longe that he came to the caſtell of darques / but he mette before with a ſhypherde whiche had tolde hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that his mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the ducheſſe ſholde come to the ſayd caſtell to dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner. &amp; ſo he rode thether but wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> robert came there &amp; the peple ſe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come they ranne away from hym lyke the hare frome the hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des one ranne &amp; ſhet hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his houſe / an other ranne in to the chyrche for fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.
<pb facs="tcp:7164:11"/> Robert ſeynge this that al the people fled from hym for fere / he began to ſygh in his herte and ſayd to hymſelfe. O almyghty god how maye this be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euery man thus fleeth frome me Nowe I perceyue that I am the mooſte myſcheuouſte and curſſedeſte wretche of this worlde / for I ſente better to be a Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we or a ſaraſyne / than a criſten man and I ſee well that I am worſte of all yll. Alas ſayde robert the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll I maye well hate and curſe myne vngracyous &amp; curſed lyfe. wherfore I am worthy to be hated of god and the worlde in this mynde heuyneſſe came Robert to the caſtell gates &amp; alyghte downe from his horſe / But there was no man that durſte abyde aboute hym nor come nygh hym to holde his horſe and he had no ſeruaunte to ſerue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but let his hors ſtonde there at the gate / and drewe oute his ſworde whiche was all blody. and incontinent toke the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye vnto the halle where the ducheſſe his moder was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ducheſſe ſawe Roberte her ſone come in this wyſe with a blodyſworde in his honde. ſhe was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a ferde &amp; wolde haue fledde awaye frome him for ſhe knewe well his condicions. Robert ſeynge that euery body dyde flee from hym &amp; that his owne mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der wolde haue fledde in lyke wyſe. he called vnto her pyteouſly a ferre and ſayd. ſwete lady moder be not aferde of me / but ſtonde ſtylle tyll I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with you &amp; flee not from me in the worſhyp of cry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes paſſion. than roberts herte beinge full of thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghte and repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wente nygher her. ſaynge thus: d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re lady moder I praye and requyre you tell me how and by what maner or by wherby commeth it
<pb facs="tcp:7164:11"/> that I am ſo vicyous and curſte for I knowe well I haue it other of you or of my fader / wherfore incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinent I hertely deſyre and praye you that ye ſhewe me the trouth here of.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the Ducheſſe deſyrede / Robert her ſone / to ſmyte of her hede. and than ſhe tolde hym how ſhe had gyuen hym to the deuyll in his concepcyon</head>
            <p>THe Ducheſſe had gretly maruaylinge wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe herde her ſone ſpeke thyſe wordes &amp; py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuouſly wepynge. With a ſorowfull herte ſaynge thus to hym. My dere ſone I require you hertely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyll ſmyte of my hede. this ſayde the lady for ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry grete pyte that ſhe had vpon hym for bycauſe ſhe had gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the deuyll in his concepcyon robert anſwered his moder with an heuy and a pyteuous there ſaynge thus. O dere moder why ſholde I do ſo that ſo moche myſchefe haue done and this ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be the worſte dede that euer I dyde. But I praye you to ſhewe me that I deſyre to wete of you / then the Ducheſſe herynge his hertely deſyre tolde vnto hym the cauſe why he was ſoo vicious and full of myſchefe and how ſhe gaue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the deuyll in his concepcion. herſelf myſprayſynge / ſayde thus vnto robert. O ſone I am the mooſte vnfortunate wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man lyuynge and I knowlege that it is all my fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te that ye be ſo curſed and wycked a lyeuer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert the deuyll toke leue of his moder.</head>
            <p>ROberte herynge his moders ſaynge he fell downe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe in a ſwoune for very greate ſorowe and laye ſtyll a longe whyle. than he reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:7164:12"/> ayene and came to hymſelf and began bytterly to wepe and complayne ſaynge thus. The fendes of hell be with grete dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to applye them to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and haue me body and ſoule. but now frome this tyme forth I forſake them &amp; all theyr werkes and wyl neuer doo more harme but good. &amp; amende my lyf &amp; leue my ſynnes and do penaunce therfore tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this Roberte ſpake to his moder / the whiche was in greate ſorowe &amp; heuyneſſe ſaynge thus. O mooſte reuerente lady moder. I hertly beſeche &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre you that it wyll pleſe you to haue me recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto my fader for I wyll take the waye to Rome to be aſſoyled of my ſynnes / whiche be innu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merable &amp; to abhomynable to recounte. Therfore I wyll neuer ſlepe one nyght there I ſlepe an other tyll I come at Rome and god wyll.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert departed frome his moder &amp; rode in to the wylderneſſe where he founde his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye.</head>
            <p>RObert in grete haſte lyghte vpon his horſe &amp; rode to the wode where he had lefte his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panye the whiche he founde. The Ducheſſe made greate lamentacion for her ſone robert whiche had taken his leue of her. And ſayd many tymes to her ſelf. Alas what ſhal I do for it is all my faute that robert my ſone hath done ſo moche myſchefe &amp; in the meane whyle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Ducheſſe made this ſorowe &amp; bewayllynge for her ſone roberte in came y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke in to the chambre &amp; as ſone as ſhe ſawe hym ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to tell hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſone robert piteuouſly wepyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / ſhewynge hym what he had ſayd &amp; done. than
<pb facs="tcp:7164:12"/> the good Duke axed her / whether robert were dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to leue his vicioꝰ lyfe. &amp; yf he were ſory for his greate offences / ye my lorde ſayde ſhe he is ſore repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunte. thenne began the duke ſore to ſygh &amp; ſayde Alas it is all in vayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> roberte thynketh to do for I fere he ſhall neuer haue power to make reſtytucy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / of the hurtes &amp; harmes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche he hath done in his lyfe. but I beſeche almyghty god to prolonge his lyf and ſende him tyme &amp; reſpyte that he maye amende his lyfe &amp; do penaunce for his ſynnes</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert tolde his companye he wolde goo to Rome for to be aſſoyled of his ſynnes.</head>
            <p>NOw is robert come ayene to his companye whiche he founde ſyttinge at dyner &amp; whan they ſawe hym they roſe vp &amp; dyde hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> roberte began to rebuke them for theyr vycyous ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge ſaynge thus my welbeloued felawes. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you in the reuerence of god / that ye wyll her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and take hede to this that I ſhall ſhewe you / ye knowe well howe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue ledde hetherto an vngraciouſe and mooſte viciouſe lyfe. robbed &amp; pyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led chyrches / forced women / rauyſſhed maydens / robbed and kylled marchauntes. We haue robbed and kylled nonnes holy aunkers preeſtes clerkes / and many other people withoute nombre haue we murdred and robbed. Wherfore we be in the waye of endles dampnacion except that god haue mercy vpon vs. Wherfore I require you euerychone for goddes ſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyll chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge youre opinion &amp; leue your abhomynable ſynnes &amp; do penaunce therfore
<pb facs="tcp:7164:13"/> for I wyll go to rome to be ſhryuen and to haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for my ſynnes. Whan Robert thus ſayd one of the theues roſe and ſayd to his companye in moc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kage. nowe ſyrs take hede the foxe wyll be an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker for he begynneth to preche. Robert mocketh faſt with vs for he is our capiteyn &amp; doth more harme al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone than al we do how thinke ye wyll he be longe thus holy. yet ſayd Robert gentyl felawes I praye you for goddes ſake leue your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions &amp; thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke on your ſoule &amp; do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for your moſte felleſt ſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es &amp; crye vpon our lorde for mercy &amp; foryeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; he wyll foryeue you wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Robert hadde ſayd thus than ſpake to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one of the theues &amp; ſayde I praye you mayſter be in peaſe / for it auayleth not what ye ſaye do but ſpende your tyme in waſte / for I nor my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany wyl not ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de our lyf for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyuynge / And all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded his ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and ſayden all w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one voyce he ſaythe trewe for and we ſholde dye / we wyll not leue our olde condy cyons and curſed lyfe. but and yf we haue done mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hurte hether to we wyll do moche more here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Robert the deuyll kylled all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye.</head>
            <p>RObert herynge the faſte &amp; wycked opynion &amp; myſcheuous purpoſe of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye wex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed angry and thoughte yf they remayne and abyde ſtylle here they wyl do greate myſchef and murdre but he wente preuely vnto the dore and ſhet it faſte and gatte a greate ſtaffe and layde one on the the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues on the hede / that he fell downe dede to the erth.
<pb facs="tcp:7164:13"/> And ſo he ſerued one after an other. tyll he had kyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led them euerychone. thenne ſayde he thus to them / ſyrs I haue rewarded you after your deſert &amp; by cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ye haue done me good ſeruyce I haue gyuen you good wages. for who ſoo euer ſerueth a good may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter he is lyke to haue good wages whan Roberte had thus done he wolde haue brente y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hous. but he conſydered the grete good that was there in wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re he let it ſtonde and ſhette faſte the dores aboute and locked them and broughte a waye the key with hym to his fader.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Robert the deuyll ſente the key of his chefe hous or theuyſſhe lodginge to his fader the Duke. of normandye and how he wente to Rome.</head>
            <p>THenne whan Robert had done all that ſayd is he toke vp his honde &amp; bleſſed hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; rode thorowe the foreſt the nexte waye to Rome. Rober<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te rode that daye ſo longe tyl that the nyghte came on and was paſſynge ſore enho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gred for he had eten noo mete of all that daye / and fortuned to come ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng by an abbaye whiche he had many tymes rob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed. and the abbot was his kynneſſman &amp; Roberte rode in to this abbaye and ſayd neuer a worde but whan the monkes ſe Robert come they were ſore a ferde and ranne awaye. ſaynge one the an other he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cometh the vngracyous Roberte. the deuyll hath broughte hym hether. whan Robert herde this and ſe them al renne awaye from hym than his ſorowe began to renewe and ſayd in hymſelfe in ſore ſygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge &amp; ſorowfull herte. I may well hate my curſed
<pb facs="tcp:7164:14"/> lyfe for euery man fleeth from me &amp; I haue ſpente my tyme vngracyouſly &amp; in euyll and curſed wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and there with all he rode ſtreyghte to the chyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che dore &amp; alyghte downe frome his hors deuoutly ſaynge his prayers to god in this wyſe. O lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu cryſte I moſte ſynfull wretche and veſſel of alle ſtinkinge ſynnes / I praye the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wylt haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy on me and preſerue and kepe me frome all daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geres and peryll / And thenne he wente &amp; ſpoke to the abbot and monkes ſo ſwetly and ſo pyteuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; amyably y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come toward hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me robert ſayde pytouſly wepinge knelynge on his knees. my lorde I knowlege myſelf that I haue gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uouſly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded you. and haue done greate harme &amp; iniurye vnto your abbay. Wherfore I require &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye you all in the honoure of cryſtes paſſyon of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyueneſſe. and than he ſpake to the abbot in this wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe my lorde abbot I praye you hertely haue me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to my lorde my fader the duke of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandye / &amp; delyuer hym this keye of the chefe hous where I haue dwelled with my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche I haue all ſlayne. to thentent that they ſholde do no more harme. &amp; in that hous lyeth all the goodes &amp; treſoure that I haue ſtolen frome you &amp; other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherfore I am ryghte ſory. and beſeche you of for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyueneſſe / and I praye you that this good maye be rendred ayene vnto ſuche people as they haue ben longinge to before. robert abode y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abbay but in the mornynge erly he wente thens. and lefte behynde hym his horſe and his ſwerde wher with all he had done grete myſchefe. and ſo he wente al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb facs="tcp:7164:14"/> towarde Rome. And on the ſame daye rode y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abbot to the duke of normandye &amp; gaue hym the ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Robert had delyuered hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; tolde the duke how he was gone to Rome. tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke gaue al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore people theyr goodes ayen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had loſte before as ferre as it coude be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in the chefe hous. we wyl ſeaſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke &amp; the abbot &amp; ſpeke of robert whiche gooth to rome warde allone with grete deuocion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Roberte came to rome for remyſſyon of his ſynnes</head>
            <p>RObert went ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ouer hylles &amp; dales al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone tyll at laſte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete payne &amp; pouerte he came to rome in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte vpon a ſhere thurſdaye at nyght &amp; on the fryday after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope hymſelf ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyne ſeruice as the cuſtome was in ſaynt peters chyrche / &amp; Robert preſed faſte to haue comen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> robert preſed ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope they ſmote hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; had hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go bac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more they ſmote hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more he preſed &amp; thro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge to gette nygh the pope &amp; ſo at laſte he gate to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; fel doune on his knees at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feet of the pope crye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a loude voyce ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thus o holy fad<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> haue mercy on me &amp; thus lay robert crye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge whyle the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were by the pope were angry y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Roberte made ſuche a noyſe &amp; wold haue dryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thens but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ſey<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge roberts grete deſyre had pite vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to his peple late hym alone for in al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can ſe he hath grete deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope ꝯmau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them al to holde there peſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <choice>
                  <abbr>betr</abbr>
                  <expan>better</expan>
               </choice> here &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtonde robert than ſayd Robert to the pope in this maner / o holy fader I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte and the greteſte
<pb facs="tcp:7164:15"/> ſynner of all this worlde / the pope toke Robert vp by the honde and ſayd to hym good frende what is your deſyre &amp; what eleth you to make all this noyſe than ſayd Roberte o holy fader I beſeche you to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon / for and I be not by you aſſoyled I am da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>outen ende for it is meruayle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuyll bereth me not awaye body &amp; ſoule ſeyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the foule innumerable &amp; ſtynky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſynne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am laden &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all more than ony man lyuynge / and in ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye are he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gyueth remedy helpe &amp; comforte to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue nede / therfore I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che you for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſyon of our lorde Iheſu cryſt to here &amp; purge me of my mooſt mortall &amp; abhomynable ſynnes wherby I am dereuered &amp; departed fro all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ioyes of heuen &amp; am wors tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Iewe / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope hery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge this demed &amp; thought in hymſelfe whether this were roberte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl / &amp; axed hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſone be ye roberte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche I haue herde ſo moche ſpekynge of / the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is worſt of al men / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> roberte anſwered &amp; ſayd ye / than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope ſayd I wyll aſſoyle you but I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iure you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye do no man harme. The pope &amp; all that were aboute hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were aferde to loke vpon roberte / roberte fell on his knees with grete de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocion &amp; repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſaynge holy fader nay as longe as I lyue I promyſe god &amp; his bleſſyd moder / wyll I neuer hurte cryſten creature / than in contynent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope toke roberte aparte &amp; herde his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon to whome roberte ſhroue hym deuoutly ſhe wynge how his moder had gyuen hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the deuyl in his concepcyon wherof the pope was ſore aferde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:15"/>
            <head>¶ How the Pope ſente Roberte thre myle without Rome to an holy heremyte.
<figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut hermit and man</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>THe Pope this herynge was gretly abaſſhed &amp; bleſſyd hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſayd to roberte / my dere ſone ye. muſte go thre myle without the towne &amp; there ye ſhal fynde an heremyte whiche is my gooſtly fader &amp; to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhall confeſſe you &amp; ſaye that I ſende you to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; he ſhal aſoyle you / roberte anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope I wyl go with a good wyll / &amp; toke his leue of the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe ſaynge god gyue me grace to do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be to the helth of my ſoule / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nyght roberte abode in rome
<pb facs="tcp:7164:16"/> for it was late / &amp; in the mornynge erly robert went out of rome towarde the place where he ſholde fyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the heremyte &amp; ſo he went ſo longe ouer hylles &amp; dales w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete deſyre to be ſhryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſynnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at laſte he come where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heremyte dwelled wherof he was glad / &amp; came to the heremyte &amp; tolde hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope had ſente hym theder to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed of hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heremyte ſayde he was hertly welcome. &amp; with in a whyle robert began to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe &amp; ſhewe his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; fyrſte he ſhewed the heremyte how his moder had gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym to the deuyl in his concepcion &amp; how he ſmote the chylderne in his youth or he coude goo allone and how he kylled his ſcole mayſter &amp; how many knyghtes he kylled at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fad<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> made hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knyght &amp; he rode thorowe his faders lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de robbyng &amp; ſtelynge forſynge of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rauiſſhy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; how he chraſte out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyen of his fad<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>s me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in diſpyte of hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; how he had kylled .vii. heremites &amp; ſhortly ſhewed hym al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer he dyde ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of his byrth tyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme. Wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myte had maruayle. but he was glad y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Robert was repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for his ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> robert had thꝰ confeſſed hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heremyte ſayd to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſone this night ye ſhal a byde here &amp; to morow I ſhal gyue you good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue to do robert y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſo curſt &amp; furious miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuous ferfull cruel &amp; proude as a lyon. is now as ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyl &amp; curteys &amp; ſwete of wordes &amp; wyſe in his de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des as euer was ony duke or prynce lyuynge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bert was ſo wery &amp; ouercomen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he coude nother ete nor drynke. but wente aparte &amp; ſayde his prayers to almyghty god prayenge hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorow his
<pb facs="tcp:7164:16"/> endeles mercy / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde kepe hym from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyon &amp; deceyte. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heremyte made roberte to lye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nyght in a lytell chapell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtode nye his celle &amp; the heremyte prayed al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nyght to our lord for Robert whiche ſawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had grete repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for his ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es and thus prayenge the heremyte fell a ſlepe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How god ſent an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel to the heremyte to ſhewe hym the penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that he ſholde gyue to Roberte for his ſynnes.</head>
            <p>THe heremyte bey<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thus a ſlepe there came to hym an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell ſaynge to hym in this wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. holy fader here &amp; take hede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſſage y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth. yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Robert wyll be ſhryuen of his ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / he muſte kepe and counterfete the wayes of a fole and be as he were dombe. &amp; he may ete no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of mete / but that he can take it from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dogges &amp; in this wyſe without ſpekynge &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfetinge the fole &amp; no thynge etynge but what he can take from the dogges muſt he be tyll tyme that it ſhall pleaſe god to ſhewe hym that his ſynne be foryeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; with this viſyon the heremyte a woke oute of his ſlepe &amp; began to remembre hymſelf of this that ſayd is / &amp; thanked our lorde of his gracious meſſage done to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the daye bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to apere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heremyte called robert vnto hym. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fayre &amp; confortable wordes ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge to hym my frende come hether to me. &amp; incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynent robert came to hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete deuocion hym co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſynge. and whan robert had ſhryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remyte ſayde thus vnto hym ſone I haue thoughte &amp; aduiſed me of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> penaunce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhal haue to gete remyſſyon of your ſynnes / In whiche ye haue gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly
<pb facs="tcp:7164:17"/> offended ayenſt god that is to wete ye muſte cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfayte &amp; playe the fole / &amp; ye maye ete no mete but that ye can take it from the dogges whan men gyue them ought / alſo ye muſt kepe you as dumbe without ſpeche &amp; lye amonge dogges for thus hath god this nyght commaunded me by his aungell to gyue you this for your penaunce and ye maye of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende no man the whyle your penaunce be a doyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / and this penaunce ye muſt do for your ſynnes in maner and forme as I haue tolde you tyll ſuche tyme as it ſhall pleaſe our lorde to ſende you worde that your ſynnes be forgyuen / roberte beynge mery and gladde thanky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge our lorde Iheſu cryſt that he was aſſoyled of his ſynnes &amp; had therfore ſo lyght penaunce as hym thoughte that it was. Nowe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Roberte leue of the heremyte / and gooth to do his grete and ſharpe penaunce whiche he helde but lyght remembrynge his grete abhomynable ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge ſynnes that he hath done all the dayes of his lyf this was a fayre myracle / for he that was ſo vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous and ſo furyous a rebell &amp; proude a ſynner / is now ſoo full of vertues and fayre condycyons and as tame as a lambe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Roberte the deuyll toke his leue of the here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myte &amp; wente agayne to Rome to do his penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he heremyte had gyuen hym.</head>
            <p>ROberte hathe taken leue of the heremyte &amp; is gone towarde Rome there for to do his pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce. And whan he came in to the cyte he began to lepe &amp; renne aboute the ſtretes makynge hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:7164:17"/> as thoughe he had ben a fole / &amp; the childeren in the ſtretes ſe Roberte renne in this wyſe and they after hym ſhoutynge and cryenge &amp; caſtynge with myre and derte and all ſuche fylth as they founde in the ſtretes and the Burgeyſes of the cyte laye in theyr wyndowes and laughed and mocked with roberte Than whan roberte had thus played the fole in ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me a certayne ſeaſon he came on a tyme to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours courte &amp; ſe that the gate dyde ſtonde open &amp; he ranne ſtreyght in to the hall / &amp; there he Ietted vp and downe from the one ende to the other ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme he wente faſt and ſomtyme ſoftely and than he hopped and ranne and other whyle he ſtode euen ſtylle / but he ſtode not longe in one place. The Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroure ſeynge Roberte thus playenge the fole. He ſayd to one of his ſeruauntes / ſe yonder is a fayre and a well fauoured yonge man / me thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth he is out of his mynde the whiche is greate domage / for he is fayre &amp; a well made man / go &amp; gyue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mete. ¶ This Emperours ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dyde as he was com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded &amp; called roberte to hym &amp; wolde haue gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome mete / but roberte wolde nother ete nor drynke / &amp; whyle roberte ſate thus at the table them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour ſawe one of his hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des whiche was bytten with an other dogge / wherfore the Emperour caſt hym a bone and the dogge caught the bone and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan to gnawe there on &amp; roberte ſey<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lepte from the table &amp; toke it from hym / but the dogge fought with roberte for the bone &amp; helde faſte the one ende &amp; roberte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ende / but roberte ſe it wolde be no better / but ſet hym downe on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; gnewe
<pb facs="tcp:7164:18"/> on the one ende of the bone &amp; the dogge on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other themperoure and they that loked here on / laughed at robert and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dogge. but Robert dyde ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gatte the bone allone &amp; laye and gnewe it for he was ſore enhongred. themperoure ſeynge that Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert was ſo ſore enhongred he caſte to an other dog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge an hoole lofe. but robert toke it frome hym &amp; bra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke it in two peces &amp; gaue the dogge half for by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe he gatte it for the dogges ſake. the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour ſeynge this lough there at &amp; ſayd to his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. We ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue here nowe the moſte folyſſhe fole and the verayſt nedy that euer I ſawe for he taketh the dogges mete from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; eteth it hymſelf therby a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may perfytely knowe that he is a naturell fole all that were in the hal gaue the dogges as moche mete as they myght ete to thentente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> robert myght fyll his belye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; whan he had filled his belly while he roſe vp and walked vp and doune in the hall with a ſtaffe in his honde / ſmytynge vpon ſtoles and ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches lyke as &amp; yf he had bene a very innocente fole. And thus walkynge he loked on euery ſyde &amp; ſawe adore where men wente in to a fayre gardyne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche gardyne there ſtode a fayre fontayne or wel and theder went Robert to drynke for he was euyll churſte and whan nyghte came on / robert folowed the forſayde dogge where ſo euer he wente the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was acuſtomed to lye euery nyghte vnder a ſtey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; there he went and layde him downe &amp; robert fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed hym vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſteyre and layde hym doune by the dogge. themperoure ſeynge this had compaſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on Robert and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that men ſholde be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:7164:18"/> hym a bedde / that he myght lye there vpon to ſle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe anone two ſeruauntes brought robert a bedde to ſlepe there on but he pointed to bere it away ayene for he had leuer to lye vpon the hard and colde erth than vpon a ſofte bedde where of themperour had greate maruayle / and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that men ſhold bere hym clene ſtrawe whiche they dyde than robert whiche was feynte and wery of goynge leyde hym downe to ſlepe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrawe. now haue this in youre myndes ye proude hertes &amp; ſynners thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke on rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes greate penaunce &amp; wylfull pouerte and how he ſo greate a gentylman borne forſoke his fader and his moder and al his frendes and his countrey and londe / &amp; al his dylycate metes &amp; drinkes &amp; gaye ray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes &amp; wordly pleſure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all that of ſuche aſtate aperteyneth how wyllyngly he hath alle forſaken for the ſaluacyon of his ſoule &amp; is gone out of a du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes bedde to dogges canell. and with dogges he ete &amp; dronke &amp; ſlepte &amp; roſe whan they roſe. &amp; in this pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce lyued roberte .vii. yeres or there aboute. &amp; the dogge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he comunly ſlept with all perceyued that he foure the better &amp; had more mete for robertes ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke than he was wonte to haue before &amp; that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyde bete hym for his ſake wherfore he began to lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue robert paſſynge well in ſo moche men myght as ſoone haue kylled hym as dryuen hym from robert</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How robert made a Iewe to kyſſe his dogges ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe at the Emperours table.</head>
            <p>IT befell vpon a tyme that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour helde a grete feſte in his palays in the cyte of rome
<pb facs="tcp:7164:19"/> to whiche feſte were aſſembled all the chefe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de amonge whome there was a Iewe whiche was receyuer of the moſte parte of all themperours lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. and whan euery man was ſette at the table ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bert walked vp &amp; doune in the hall hauy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his dog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge in his armes playenge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fole as he was wonte to do. &amp; thus came to the table behynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foreſayde Iewe whiche was ſette at themperours table and Robert come behynde his backe and knocked hym on the ſholder the Iewe felte hym and tourned his face ſhortly behynde hym and robert hadde vp his dogges arſe redy and ſette it vpon the Iewes face. Themperoure &amp; his lordes this ſcynge / laughed &amp; had good game there at. but the Iewe was wroth &amp; foule aſhamed but he durſt ſaye no thynge at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Than robert ſet doune his dogge &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent the dogge lepte vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table &amp; dyde ſo moche with his mouth &amp; fete that he caſte downe al the mete vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the table. And in this maner Robert ſpente his tyme euer withoute ſpeky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. lyke as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heremite had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; euer he dyde ſom madde or mery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyte to cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour to laugh or to be mery.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Roberte threwe downe a bryde on a foule donge hyll and how he put a lyuynge catte in to an hote ſethynge potte with podred beſe.</head>
            <p>IT befell on a tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was a bryde ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de goo to chyrche to be wedded. Whiche was gayly aparelled as to a bryde aperteyned Roberte ſeynge this bryde thus gayly arayed. toke her by the ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; led her thorough a paſſyng foule donge hyll
<pb facs="tcp:7164:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> and there made her fall &amp; fouled her gaye araye &amp; than he ranne lyghtely a waye ſhoutynge &amp; laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge and ranne vnto the brydes kytchen where her dynner was apareyled and caughte a lyuynge cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and caſte her in to the potte of pouldred befe / </p>
            <p>The whiche incontine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was tolde to themperoure where at he and all his lordes laughed and hadde grete game there at. &amp; they loued Roberte paſſynge well for he made moche myrth without harme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the ſeneſſhal had gadred a greate armye of men of warre of ſaraſins &amp; layde ſyege to Rome be cauſe the Emperour wolde not gyue hym his dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghter in maryage.
<figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut battle</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:20"/>
            <p>IN the mene ſeaſon whyle Roberte was thus in Rome doinge his penaunce as is forſayde whiche dured ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yeres or there aboute in the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perours courte. the whiche emperoure hadde a fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re doughter. but ſhe was borne dombe &amp; neuer ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / &amp; themperous ſeneſchall dyuerſe tymes had de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyred this doughter in maryage of the Emperoure but he wolde neuer graunte hym her / wherfore the ſeneſchall was gretly moued and angry therwith themperoure. for he thoughte he myght haue won of hym his empyre by forſe and myght in ſo moche the ſeneſchal came vpon a tyme with a greate hoſte of ſaraſyns &amp; layde ſyege to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Rome where of themperour had grete maruayle. &amp; wondred tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themperour gadred &amp; aſſembled al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes barons aſkynge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell ſaynge thus my lordes gyue me good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye withſtonde this hethe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dogges whiche haue layde ſyege here to oure Cyte wherfore I take greate thoughte for they kepe all my londe vnder theyr ſubieccyon &amp; they wyll bry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion yf that god not of his endles mercy helpe vs not. wherfore I praye you eurychone to go fyght with them with al our power &amp; myght &amp; dry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away than anſwered the lordes &amp; knyghtes all with one aſſente ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſouerayne lord your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyll is good &amp; wyſe. Wherfore we be all redy to go with you. &amp; gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> batayle &amp; defende our ryghte both londe &amp; cyte themperoure thanked the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this anſwere &amp; was glad therof &amp; made proclamacion thorowe out all his londes &amp; cytees that euery man olde &amp; yonge that were able to bere armes ſhold ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:7164:20"/> them redy to go fyght ayenſt theyr mooſt cruell enmyes the ſaraſyns whiche were comen in to the londe. &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent whan this proclamacyon was done amonge the comyns euery man was wyllyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge &amp; redy to go with themperour to fyght &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de theyr ryght and ſo they went forthe in a fayre ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with themperoure to fyghte vpon theyr mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal enmyes the hethen dogges / And for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour had moche mo people than the ſenſhal yet the ſeneſhal had wonne the felde / hadde not god of his greate marcy ſent theder Robert to reſyſte and helpe the romaynes in theyr exſtreme neceſſyte.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How our ſauyour iheſu hauynge compaſſion on the cryſten blod ſente Robert by his au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell a white hors &amp; harneys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge hym to go reſewe and helpe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> romayns ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hethe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dogges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaraſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</head>
            <p>THe Emperour &amp; the romayns wente to the batayle as ſayd is ayenſt the ſaraſyns. &amp; ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte was at home. Where he was accuſtomed to walke in the gardyne to a fontayne or well to drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. &amp; this was on the ſame daye that the emperour with his hoſte ſholde gyue batayle ayenſte the ſara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyns. than there came a voyce out of heuen ſent fro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me our lorde aboue ſaynge in this maner. Roberte god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth you by me that ye inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynent arme you with this harneys and lyghte vpon this horſe that god hath ſente you. &amp; ryde in all haſte poſſyble and reſcue the emperour &amp; his people. Robert hery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god was abaſſhed in his mynde. and durſt not do ayenſt goddes commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de
<pb facs="tcp:7164:21"/> but in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynent he armed hym &amp; lepte on that hors without ony taryenge and rode his waye / the Emperours doughter whiche I tolde you of before ſtode at a wyndowe &amp; ſawe Roberte thus armed on hors backe than yf ſhe coude haue ſpoken ſhe wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de haue tolde it but ſhe coude not ſpeke for ſhe was dombe but ſhe remembred and bare it ſurely in her my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de roberte thus horſt &amp; harnayſt rode in to them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perours hooſt whiche he ſawe was ſore ouerpreſſed with theyr enemyes the Turkes in ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had not god &amp; roberte reſcued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cryſten men had ben all ſlayne / but wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> roberte was come in to thooſt he put hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt preſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> turkes &amp; faught &amp; lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de on eche ſyde on theſe curſed hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / there a man myght haue ſene / armes / legges / heedes tomble on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / he ſmote to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de both hors &amp; man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer roſe after / it was a worlde to ſe the murdre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> roberte dyde amonge the dampned dogges the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raſyns / ſo to make ſhort tale roberte dyde ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaraſyns were cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrayned to flye awaye &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour helde the felde &amp; had the vyctorye of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Roberte torned agayne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſayd fontay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne &amp; there vnarmed hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whan he had thus ſubdued &amp; vaynquyſſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaraſyns &amp; put them to flyght.</head>
            <p>NOw hath the Empererour goten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felde &amp; the honoure thanked be god &amp; roberte is tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned agayne to the ſayd fontayne &amp; there vnarmed hym &amp; layde the harnays on the hors whiche incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynent was vanyſſhed awaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man coude kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we nor perceyue where he become and Roberte bode
<pb facs="tcp:7164:21"/> ſtyll ſtondynge by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fontayne / themperours dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſeynge this had grete meruayll of this &amp; wolde haue tolde it forthe but ſhe was dombe &amp; coude not ſpeke / roberte had a race in his face whiche he gote in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> batayll / but he was none otherwyſe hurte / the Emperour was glad &amp; thanked god of his vyctory ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe dogges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaraſyns &amp; thus beynge me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry he came home to his palays &amp; whan they were al ſet to dyner roberte preſented hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe before thempe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour as he was wonte to do play<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fole &amp; makyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be as a fore reherſed is themperour reioyſed in hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe whan he ſe roberte for he loued hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge well &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he perceyued roberts hurte in his face &amp; thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome of his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes had hurte hym whyle he was out / wherfore he was angry &amp; ſayd / here in this courte be ſome enuyous men / for whyle we haue ben out at batayle they haue beten &amp; hurte this poore Innocente creature in his face whiche is grete ſynne for thoughe he be a fole he doth no man harme ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them all vpon a gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te payne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſholde do hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harme / yf they dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de they ſhold be punyſſhed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all other ſhold beware by them / than themperour began to axe his knygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes yf there were ony of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> coude tell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyght with the whyte hors y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came preuely in to the felde &amp; ſo valyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly reſcued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perours doughter this herynge poynted themperour her fader y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte / but themperour vnderſtode not what his dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghter mente what ſhe poy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted / for ſhe coude not ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / wherfore he called her mayſtres to hym &amp; axed her what his doughter mente by her poyntynge / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7164:22"/> her mayſtreſſe anſwered and ſayde your doughter menes by her pointynge that this daye ye haue got<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten the bataylle and victorye thorowe the helpe of youre fole robert &amp; the race that is in his face he ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the gotten it in the batayle. the Emperoure vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtondyng the mynde and intent of his doughter he was angry and ſayde to her mayſters. ye ſholde te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che &amp; lerne my doughter wyſdome &amp; no folye ne pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſhneſſe wher with all I am myſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent the dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſeynge that her fader was angry pointed no mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re not withſtondynge ſhe wyſt well that it was tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we that ſhe pointed and mente / for in as moche as ſhe had ſene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell brynge hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hors &amp; harneis This remaynde in this wyſe a certeyne ſeaſon and after that the ſaraſyns were put to flyghte by the romayns as ſayde is yet came the ſeneſſhal agayne with moche more company &amp; layde ſyege to Rome &amp; the romaynes ſholde haue loſt the fylde ayen had not the knyghte on the white horſe bene to whome god ſent horſſe and harnays as he had done before to make ſhorte tale this knyght dyde ſo moche that the ſaraſyns were put to flyght &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> romayns won<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the felde &amp; victorye as they dyde before. there were ſome of the emperours meyny layde wayte where this knyghte became. But as ſoone as the batayle was done he was gone noo man coude tell were he was become ſaue oonly the Emperours doughter whiche ſe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fontayne agayne vnarmynge hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Robert gatte the thyrde batayle as he dyde before whiche ſhe kepte ſecrete.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:22"/>
            <p>IN a ſhorte tyme after this the ſeneſſhal tour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned ageyne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a moche greter power than he hadde before &amp; layd ſyege to rome and yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroure rode to the batayle he commaunded his knyghtes &amp; barones to take good hede fro whens that knyghte came w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the white horſſe and what he was and where he became for he hadde grete deſyre to knowe what he was / The knyghtes anſwered it ſholde be done the daye came that they muſt ryde forth to the batayle and ſerteyne of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beſt knyghtes rode pryuely into a wood that ſtode a lytell there be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyde &amp; there they wayted whiche waye the knyghte on the white horſſe ſholde come to the batayle but they loſte theyr laboure for they coude not tell whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s he come / But whan they ſawe hym in the batayle they rode towarde him to helpe hym and receiue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſame batayle was ſore foughten on both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes / but the ſaraſyns loſte there courage for robert layde on ſo greate and myghty ſtrokes that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myght ſtonde vnder his honde ſo that in concluſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Robert dyde ſo moche and ſo valyantly that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raſyns were put to the dyſcomfyture where of the Emperour was greatly enioyed and the ſeneſſhall with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaraſyns were paſſynge angry and ſore mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued therwith all.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How one of the emperoures knyghtes hurte Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bert in the thyghe with a ſpere.</head>
            <p>THan wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this batayle was done euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rode home and Roberte wolde haue tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned agayne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fontayne to vnarme hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he was
<pb facs="tcp:7164:23"/> wonte to do before / but the foreſayd knyghtes we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re torned agayne in to the wode / to a wayte for the knyght with the whyte hors and whan they ſawe hym come they rode all at ones out of the wode &amp; cryed with a loude voyce ſaynge vnto hym. O no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knyght tarye &amp; ſpeke with vs / and tell vs who that ye be &amp; whens &amp; out of what londe ye come / to the entent that we maye ſhewe it to the Emperour whiche ſpecyally he deſyreth for to knowe. Roberte this herynge was ſore a ſhamed &amp; ſmote his why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hors with his ſporres flyngynge ouer hylles and ouer valeyes for bycauſe he wolde not be knowen but there folowed hym a bolde knyght / well horſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpere wenynge to haue kylled his whyte hors but be myſte and ſmote roberte in the thyghe with his ſpere / and the ſpere heed brake of &amp; ſtacke ſtyll in his thyghe but yet for all this he coude gete no knowlege of the knyght with the whyte hors for he rode from them all euerychonc / wherof they were paſſynge ſory. Roberte rode ſo ſore tyll at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt he came to the fontayne &amp; vnarmed hym &amp; layde the harnays on the hors as he had done before whiche in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynent was vanyſſhed awaye &amp; gone &amp; he dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we out the ſpere heed out of his thyghe &amp; hyd it by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene two grete ſtones by the fontayne than he lay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de grece &amp; moſſe vpon his wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de for he durſt let no man loke therto / for fere he ſholde haue bene kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. And all this ſawe &amp; marked the Emperours doughter / forbycauſe ſhe ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Roberte was a fayre &amp; wel fauoured yonge knyght ſhe began to caſt her loue vnto hym. And whan Roberte had dreſſed his
<pb facs="tcp:7164:23"/> wounde he came in to the halle / to gete hym ſome mete &amp; he halted as lytel as he coude &amp; kepte it ſecre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> almooſt no man coude perceyue it &amp; ſuffred more payne a thouſande tymes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſemed by hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Shortly after this came home y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knyght y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had hur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te Roberte. And began to recou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour how the knyghte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whyte hors had out ryden hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; how he had hurte hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſore ayenſt his wyll. And ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour. I beſeche you my lorde Emperour here what I ſhall tell you how / and in what maner ye ſhall knowe who he is that hath holpen you it is beſt ye make a proclamacyon &amp; publyſſhe thrughe out your Empyre / &amp; yf there be ony knyght in why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te harnays and a whyte hors that he be brought to your preſence and that he brynge with hym the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re heed where with all he was hurte in his thyghe ſhewynge the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye gyue hym your dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to wyfe and halfe your Empyre with her / them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour this herynge was of his counſeyll very glad and in contynent in all haſte proclamed and puply<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed thrughe out all his Empyre and thought that the knyght had gyuen hym good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyll.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the Seneſhall thruſte a ſpere heed in to his thyghe wenynge to haue begyled themperour and to haue wonne his doughter therby.</head>
            <p>IT befell in ſhorte tyme after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Seneſhal hadde knowlege and vnderſtandynge of the Emperoures proclamacyon and howe he myghte wynne themperoures doughter whiche he had ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny tymes bene aboute he dyde grete dylygence and
<pb facs="tcp:7164:24"/> cauſed to be ſought &amp; goten a whyte hors and why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te harnays &amp; thryſte a ſpere heed in his thyghe we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge therby to deceyue themperoure and to gete his doughter to wyfe / and whan this was done he commaunded all his men to arme theym and rode with hym to the Emperour and he rode ſo ſore tyll he came to Rome with grete royalte and ſolace &amp; without ony taryenge he rode ſtreyght to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſaynge to hym in this wyſe / my lorde I am he that you ſo valyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly many tymes receyued thre tymes I haue cauſed you to haue honour &amp; vyctory ayenſt the curſed ſaraſyns / themperour thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynge vpon no treaſon nor dyſſeyte ſayd ye be a valyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; a wyſe knyght but I had wente the contrarye for we haue taken you for a vylayne and a forſworne knyght / the Seneſhall was very angry &amp; ſore mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued here withall and anſwered themperour ſhortly and angerly / my lorde Emperour meruayll you no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynge here of for I am not ſuche a cowarde as ye wene that I be &amp; thus ſaynge he toke out the ſpere heed and ſhewed it the Emperoure and vncouered the wounde the whiche he had made hym ſelfe in his thyghe the knyght ſtode by whiche that hurte Roberte before and began to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe in his mynde for he ſe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was not the heed of the ſpere but he durſt ſaye nothynge for fere leeſt the Seneſhall wolde haue kylled hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wyll leue now of the Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſhall &amp; ſpeke of Roberte whiche is amonge dog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers ſore wounded as ye haue herde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How god ſente his aungell to the heremyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he
<pb facs="tcp:7164:24"/> ſholde go to rome and ſeke Roberte for he had full done his penaunce.</head>
            <p>THe heremyte whiche ye haue herde of before that ſhroue and ſette Roberte his penaunce laye on a nyght in his ſelle and ſlepte and thus ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge there came to hym a voyce / and badde hym lyghtly a ryſe and go to Rome to the place where Roberte was doynge his penaunce / and the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell tolde the heremyte all the doynges of Roberte ſhewynge how that his penaunce was fuldone and that god hadde forgyuen hym his ſynnes wherof the heremyte was verye gladde and in the mornyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge eerly he roſe and wente to Romewarde / and in lyke wyſe in the ſame mornynge the Seneſhal roſe be tyme and wente to Rome to the Emperoure to deſyre and haue his doughter accordynge to the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blycacyon and crye / the whiche the Emperour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented her to hym without ony longe aduyſement / But whan the doughter vnderſtode that ſhe was gyuen to the Seneſhall ſhe raylled and raged as though ſhe hadde ben wood and madde ſhe tare her here from her heed and all to tore her clothes but it myght nothynge auayll her for ſhe was conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and muſt be arayed lyke a bryde and an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroures doughter whiche ſholde be maryed and the Emperour ladde her by the hande hymſelfe to the chyrche royally accompanyed with lordes and ladyes and gentylwomen but the doughter made the greteſt ſorowe of the worlde in ſo moche that no man coude content her mynde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:25"/>
            <head>¶ How the Emperours doughter thrughe the gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of god began for to ſpeke the fyrſt that euer ſhe ſpake in her lyfe.</head>
            <p>THan as the Emperour with all his eſtate was come in to the chyrche the Emperures doughter whiche was dumbe ſholde marye the Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſhall there dyde our lorde a fayre myracle for the loue of the holy man Roberte to the entente he ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be exalted / whome euery body helde for a fole and with hym mocked whan the preeſt ſholde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn the ſeruyce &amp; to marye the Seneſhall and this yonge mayde togyder / the doughter thoroughe the grace of god began to ſpeke to the Emperour her fader in this wyſe / fader I holde you not wyſe but fer ouer ſene in that ye byleue / that this proude fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe traytour telleth you / for all that he telleth you it lyes / but here in this towne is a holy and deuoute perſone / for whoſe ſake god hath gyuen me my ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wherfore I loue hym in my herte for I haue all waye ſene and marked his valyaunce and holynes but noo man wolde byleue me what poyntynge or ſygnes that I made / than the Emperour this he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge was almooſt out of his my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de for Ioye whan he herde his doughter ſpeke whiche neuer ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore / wherby he knewe well ynoughe the Seneſhal this herynge was wood angry and foule aſhamed and lyghte vpon his hors and rode awaye and all his companye the pope there beynge preſente axed the mayde who the man was that ſhe ſpoke of / than the mayde ladde the pope and the Emperoure her
<pb facs="tcp:7164:25"/> fader to the fontayne where Roberte was wonte to arme and vnarme hym and there ſhe toke out the ſpere heed from bytwene the two ſtones where Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte had hydde it / and than ſhe cauſed the ſpere to be brought forth where of this heed was broken / whiche was lyghtly broughte to her and that heed &amp; the ſpere Ioyned togyder in one as cloes as they had not be broken / than ſayd the mayde to the pope we haue had thre tymes vyctorye by his noble va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyaunce ayenſt the myſcreaunt Saraſyns / for I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue thre tymes ſene his hors and harnays wherwith he hath thre tymes armed and vnarmed hym / but I can not tell who brought hym that hors and har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nays nor vnto whome he delyuered it / but I knowe well that whanke hadde done he layde hym ſelfe downe by the dogges / and the mayden ſayd vnto the Emperour her fader in this wyſe / this is he that hath ſaued your londes and your honoure and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te you vyctorye of the hethen hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des the Saraſyns wherfore ye ought of deute to rewarde hym / and yf it pleaſe you we wyll go all to hym and ſpeke with hym / than wente they for the pope the Emperour and the doughter with all the Lordes and Ladyes vnto Roberte whome they founde lyenge amonge dogges they folowed hym and dyde hym reuerence but Roberte anſwered them not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the heremyte fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Roberte and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded hym to ſpeke ſaynge to hym that his penaunce was full done and his ſynnes forgyuen.
<pb facs="tcp:7164:26"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut hermit and man</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>THe Emperoure ſpake to Roberte &amp; ſayd I praye you ſwete frende come to me &amp; ſhewe me youre thyghe for I wyll nedes ſe / whan Roberte herde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour ſaye theſe wordes he wyſt well ynoughe wherfore he was comen to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but he lete hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thoughe he had not vnderſtonden hym &amp; Roberte dyde many madde conceytes to make the pope &amp; themperour to laughe &amp; forgate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of / but the pope ſpake to Roberte &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iured hym in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on the croſſe dyed for our redem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon that yf it be goddes wyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt ſpoken y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſpeke now vnto vs / and than Roberte roſe vp
<pb facs="tcp:7164:26"/> tyke a toie and gaue the pope his bleſſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and here withall Roberte loked behynde hym &amp; ſawe the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remyte that ſet hym his penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; as ſoone as the heremyte ſe Roberte whiche he had longe ſought he cryed to hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a loude voyce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man myght here hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were there my frende harken vnto me I knowe well that ye be Roberte that men calle the deuyll but now ye be in grace and conceyte with al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myghty god and for that foule and hydeous name ye ſhall haue a fayre name &amp; be called the ſeruaunt of god ye be he that hath ſaued this londe from the Saraſyns / wherfore I praye you that ye ſerue and worſhyp god as ye haue done hyder to / for our lorde ſendeth me now to you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundynge you to ſpeke and no more to conterfeyte the fole / for it is goddes wyll &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement / for he hath forgyuen you all your ſynnes for bycauſe ye haue made ſatyſfaccion &amp; ful done your penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / whan Roberte herde this he fell lyghtly on his knees &amp; lyfte vp his hondes towarde heuen ſaynge thus. I gyue lande &amp; than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to god creature of heuen &amp; erth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the to forgyue me myne abhomynable &amp; grete ſynnes thrughe ſo lytell &amp; lyght penaunce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue done therfore / whan the pope the Emperour &amp; the doughter &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were there preſente herde Roberte ſpeke thus ſwetely they were all here of gretely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed &amp; had grete meruayll here of / themperour ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge his noble valyaunce vertue &amp; curteſye that in hym was &amp; wolde haue gyuen hym his doughter to wyf / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heremyte wolde not it ſholde be ſo / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore euery man departed and wente home.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:27"/>
            <head>¶ Howe Roberte tourned agayne to Rome for to marye the Emperours doughter by the commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement and wyll of god.</head>
            <p>NOw the ſtorye telleth as after that Roberte had remyſſyon of his ſynnes &amp; was gone to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde his countre / than out of Rome god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded hym thre tymes by an aungell that he ſholde tourne agayne to Rome and to marye the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours doughter whiche loued hym paſſyngly well and he ſholde haue by her a ſone wherby the cryſten byleue ſholde be encreaſed and forte fyed and defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded Roberte at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god tourned agayne to Rome and maryed themperours dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter with grete tryumphe &amp; ſolace / for themperour &amp; all the Romayns were therof very gladde / this bry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dale was royally kepte and euery man that ſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte loued and lyked hym aboue all other / and the people ſayd one to an other that they were gretely beholdynge to Roberte that he had redemed them from theyr mortall enmyes the ſaraſyns this feeſt was grete and notable and deured .xiiii. dayes and whan the feeſt and brydale was done Roberte wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de departe with his lady in to Normandye to vyſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te his fader and moder / and toke his leue of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour whiche gaue hym many royall and greate gyftes as gold &amp; ſyluer &amp; precyous ſtones of dyuers colours / alſo themperour gaue hym knyghtes and ſquyers to ryde &amp; conduyte hym in to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How Roberte &amp; his lady came to rowane in Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandye with grete honour and worſhyp.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:27"/>
            <p>ROberte &amp; his lady rode ſo ferre tyll they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in to Normandye in to the noble Cyte of rowane with grete myrth &amp; ſolace / where they were receyued with greate tryumphe for the comyntees of the countre were ſorye and in grete heuynes that theyr duke. Robertes fader was dyſceſed forbycau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was a wyſe and a renomed prynce. A lytell beſyde Rowane dwelled a curſed knyghte whiche had done the ducheſſe grete wronge and ſuppreſſed many knyghtes after her huſbondes dyſceaſe. But whan Roberte was comen euery man drad hym &amp; dyde hym grete reuerence and worſhyp / than ſome ſayd we wende he had ben deed and all the lordes and burgeys of Rowane gadred them togyder and with greate honoure and reuerence they receyued Roberte and helde hym as theyr lorde and ſoueray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. And whan they had receyued hym honourably they ſhewed hym of this before ſayd knyghte / he had many tymes ſuppreſſe &amp; done wronge to his moder ſythen the deth of his fader / than whan ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte herde &amp; vnderſtode this he ſente lyghtly men of armes to take the ſayd knyght / the whiche dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſo moche that they toke hym / and brought hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Roberte whiche made hym to be hanged wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the duches was ryght gladde / but ſhe was mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che more gladder that Roberte her ſone was come home for ſhe wende he had ben deed / &amp; whan rober<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and his moder were thus togyder / he recounted vnto her howe the Emperoure hadde gyuen hym his doughter in maryage / and how he hadde done his penaunce / the ducheſſe herynge her ſones wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:7164:28"/> ſhe began to wepe very ſore / for bycauſe he had ſuffred ſo grete pouerte and penaunce / thoroughe his defaute.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How the Emperour ſente a meſſanger vnto the duke Roberte that he ſholde come and reſcue hym ayenſt the Seneſhall.</head>
            <p>IN the meane ſeaſon whyles Robert was thus at Rowane with his moder and his ladye in grete Ioye and ſolace / there came a meſſanger fro the Emperour vnto Roberte / whiche dyde hym re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence and ſaynge thus vnto hym / my lorde duke the Emperour hath ſente me hyther to you and he prayeth you for to come and reſcue hym ayenſt the falſe traytoure the Seneſhall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaraſyns whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue layde ſyege to Rome / whan Roberte her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de theſe wordes he was ſorye in his mynde for them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour / and ſhortly aſſembled as many men of ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes as he coude gete in his londe of Normandy / &amp; forth withall rode with them towarde Rome to hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe and ſocoure the Emperoure / but before he cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de come thyder the falſe traytour the Seneſhal had ſlayne the Emperour / whiche was grete pyte / but Roberte wente ſtreyght in to Rome / &amp; lyghtly with all his power and myght wente ayenſt the Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall. And whan Roberte aſpyed the falſe traytour he deſcryed hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaynge thus / abyde thou falſe tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure / now thou ſhalte neuer eſcape my hondes yf thou abyde me in the felde / for thou arte now nygh thy lyues ende / thou dydeſt put ones a ſpere heed in thy thyghe for to haue deceyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romayns / defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:7164:28"/> now thy lyfe ayenſt me for thou ſhalte neuer eſca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe myn hondes / and thou haſt alſo ſlayne my lorde the Emperour / wherfore thou ſhalte be well rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded after that thou haſte deſerued. And with theſe wordes Roberte with a greate deſyre / and myghty courage rode in contynent vnto the Seneſhall and gaue hym ſuche a ſtroke on the helmette that he clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue helmet and heed vnto the teeth / and in contynent the traytour fell downe deed vnto the erth / and Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte made hym to be brought in to Rome to the en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente that he ſholde there be ſlayne to reuenge the ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maynes / the whiche was done in the preſence of all the people that were in Rome / and in this wyſe fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed that traytoure the Seneſhall his lyfe and had a ſhamfull deth / wherby men maye make and take hede that it is greate folye to coueyte or deſyre thynges paſſynge theyr degre / for &amp; the Seneſhall had not deſyred the Emperours doughter the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che paſſed and exceded ferre aboue his degre / he had not dyed this ſhamful deth / but myght haue lyued and the Emperour alſo / &amp; haue dyed good frendes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ How y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the duke Roberte tourned agayne to Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wane after he had made the Seneſhal to be ſlayne.</head>
            <p>ROberte the duke defended the cyte of Rome from theyr enemyes. And than he tourned agayne with all his companye vnto Rowane to his wyfe whiche was paſſynge ſorowfull and penſyfe But whan ſhe herde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the traytoure the Seneſhall hadde ſlayne her fader / ſhe was almooſt out of her mynde. But Robertes moder comforted her in the
<pb facs="tcp:7164:29"/> beſt maner that ſhe coude or myght. And for to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſhortly an ende of our matre &amp; ſo to fynyſſhe this booke we wyll lette paſſe to wryte of the grete dole and ſorowe of the yonge ducheſſe / and ſpeke of the duke Roberte whiche in his youth was abte to all myſchefe and vyce and all vngracyouſnes without ony meaſure or reaſon for he was a more deuourer and a more vengeable than ony lyon nothynge ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge / nor on no man hauy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge mercy nor pyte. And after this he lyued .vii. yere in grete penaunce lyke a wylde man without ony ſpeche and lyke a dumbe beeſt etynge and drynkynge with dogges and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re after was he exalted and honoured of them whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che before dyde holde hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a fole or an innocente and mocked with hym. This Roberte lyued longe in vertue and honoure with that noble lady his wyfe / and he was beloued and dradde of hygh and lowe degre / for he dyde ryght and Iuſtyce / as well ouer the ryche as ouer the poore kepynge his londe in reſte and in peace / and he begotte a chylde with her / the whiche he called Rycharde / whiche dyde afterwarde many noble actes and dedes of armes with grete Charlemayne kynge of fraunce / for he dyde helpe hym for to gete and fortefye the cryſten fayth and he made alwayes grete warre vpon the Saraſyns. And he lyued in his londe in reſte &amp; pea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / and was beloued of poore and ryche / and all his comente loued hym / in lyke wyſe as Roberte his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der was beloued / for they lyued both deuoutly and in vertue / wherfore I praye god that we may ſo ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in this lyfe / that after this lyfe we may optayne
<pb facs="tcp:7164:29"/> and come to euerlaſtynge lyfe. To the whiche bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vs he / that bought vs and all mankynde / with his precyous blode &amp; bytter paſſyon. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>
            <l>Thus endeth the lyfe of Robert the deuyll.</l>
            <l>That was the ſeruaunt of our lorde</l>
            <l>And of his condycyons that was full euyll.</l>
            <l>Enprynted in London by Wynkyn the worde.</l>
         </trailer>
         <trailer>¶ Here endeth the lyfe of the mooſt ferefulleſt / and vnmercyfulleſt / and myſcheuous Roberte the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll whiche was afterwarde called the ſeruaunte of our lorde Iheſu cryſt.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Enprynted in fleteſtrete in the ſygne of the ſonne by Wynkyn de worde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printers_device">
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:30"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Wynkyn de Worde's device</figDesc>
                  <head>Wynkyn. de. Worde.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7164:30"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
